Finding Aid for the Frank C. Gates papers
Bentley Historical Library
Frank C. Gates papers
1871-2000
1907-1955
Bentley Historical Library
Gates, Frank C. (Frank Caleb), 1887-1955
0142 Aa 2
6.4 linear feet (in 8 boxes)
Frank C. Gates was a professor of botany at the University of the Philippines, 1912-1915. He later taught botany and biology at the University of Michigan Biological Station and Kansas State College. His collection includes personal and biographical material, including a biography written by his son, David M. Gates; personal and professional correspondence; journals; academic and research material, such as birding and botany notebooks as well as descriptions and drafts of writings pertaining to Philippine vegetation and travels in the Philippines; and photographic material, including lantern slides, photographs, and photograph albums.
The collection was the gift of Mr. David M. Gates (donor no. 9022 ) and came to the library in October, 2000. Additional material arrived in 2016.
The collection is open for research.
No further additions to the records are expected.
Frank Caleb Gates was born on September 12, 1887 in Ravenswood, Illinois. He was a lifelong student and teacher of science, primarily interested in botany, ecology, and biology. He developed his interest in science at an early age and was able to expand his knowledge through the use of libraries close to his suburban Chicago home. He completed his undergraduate education at the University of Illinois in 1910, majoring in botany. He continued his graduate and doctoral studies at the University of Michigan, receiving his Ph.D. in Botany in 1912. Gates departed for a faculty position at the University of the Philippines in 1912, where he remained until 1915. During this time Gates documented, through photographs and writings, his observations of the diverse vegetation, geography, and climate of that region as well as the culture of its people and the students he taught. Gates returned home from the Philippines by way of Japan, China, Hawaii, and the Western United States.
Upon his return he married Margaret (Madge) Murray Thompson in Cleveland, Ohio on June 11, 1915. Madge and Frank were neighbors while growing up in Ravenswood, Illinois and the two corresponded frequently throughout Gates's time in the Philippines. Between the years 1915 and 1918, Gates taught botany and biology at the University of Michigan Biological Station during the summer and at Carthage College in Carthage, Illinois during the regular school term. Gates moved on to teach for many years at Kansas State College. The Gates adopted two children, David Murray and Margaret Elizabeth. Frank Gates died in 1955.
The Frank C. Gates papers are dated from 1871-2010 and include biographical and personal material, such as a biographical monograph authored by his son, David M. Gates; personal and professional correspondence; journals; publications; research notebooks; postcards, photographs, photographic negatives, photograph albums, and lantern slides. In addition to documenting Gates's time spent teaching botany at the University of the Philippines and exploring the vegetation of the Philippines Islands (1912-1915), this collection also documents his personal and professional life, service in World War I, and research interests and efforts.
Arranged in five series: 1. Personal and biographical material. 2. Correspondence. 3. Journals. 4. Academic and research material. 5. Visual material.
Bird watching.; Botany -- Philippines.; Forests and forestry -- Philippines.; Philippines -- Description and travel.; Plants -- Philippines.; Lantern slides.; Photograph albums.; Photographs.; Postcards.; Gates, David Murray, 1921-; Gates, Frank C. (Frank Caleb), 1887-1955.; University of the Philippines -- Faculty.
- Personal and biographical material, 1922; circa 1931-1942; 1946-1954; 1998; 2000; 0.5 linear feet
  The Personal and biographical material series (scattered dates, 0.5 linear feet) consists of Frank C. Gates's Phi Kappa Phi diploma; maps of major trips; recollections ("testimonials") of Gates collected by his son, David M. Gates; and one bound monograph documenting the life of Frank Caleb Gates written by David Gates, and published in July 2000. The book includes information about the Gates family lineage, the educational background and interests of both Frank and Margaret Thompson (Madge) Gates, academic accomplishments of Gates, family travel, excerpts from published and unpublished writings, photographs, and a bibliography of works written by or about Mr. Gates.
  - Phi Kappa Phi diploma, 1922 (Box 4)
  - Major Trips maps, circa 1931-1942; 1946-1954; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - F.C. Gates testimonials, circa 1998; 2000 (Box 4)
  - Monograph: Frank Caleb Gates Botanist and Ecologist and his Companion Margaret Thompson Gates by David Murray Gates, July 2000 (Box 1)
  - Maps and other material, circa 1942-1947 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, circa 1907-1955; 0.5 linear feet
  The Correspondence series (circa 1907-1955, 0.5 linear feet) contains chronologically arranged personal and professional correspondence of Frank C. Gates and includes letters written by Gates to his parents, siblings, and fiancé (Madge), and the University of the Philippines during his time in the Philippine Islands as well as correspondence relating to Gates's service in World War I, particularly letters between himself and various family members (such as Ralph Gates).
  Included among the correspondence series are a limited amount of mementos and other ephemeral materials collected by Mr. Gates during his travels in the Philippines, including passenger lists, photographs, business cards, small diaries, and sketches.
  - Personal, 1912-1915; 1918-1919; 1924-1925; 1955
    - August 1912-September 1912 (Box 1)
    - September 1912-December 1912 (Box 1)
    - Frank C. Gates (FCG) Letters and photographs to Madge from the Philippines, circa 1913-1915 (Box 4)
    - January 1913-August 1913 (Box 1)
    - September 1913-April 1914 (Box 1)
    - May 1914-May 1915 (Box 1)
    - World War I letters from Ralph and Bill, 1918 (Box 4)
    - Letters from Frank C. Gates and Madge to Uncle William Pillsbury, 1918-1919 (Box 4)
    - War Service correspondence, 1918-1919; 1924-1925; 1955; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Professional, 1907-1926; 1928; 1935; 1941
    - Correspondence and other material, 1907-1920; 1928; 1941; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - 1912-1915 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and other material (including a letter of student Harrison Welshonse's drowning), circa 1915-1926; 1935; 1941 (Box 4)
    - Letter from Gleason to F.C. Gates in 1930 (includes photograph), circa 1930 (Box 4)
- Journals, circa 1871-1882; 1907-1955; 1 linear foot
  The Journals series (circa 1871-1881 and 1907-1955, 1 linear foot) contains journals, notebooks, and related material written by Frank C. Gates that document his personal and professional life. Also contained in this series is one religious journal authored by Frank C. Gates's father, William Spaulding (W.S.) Gates.
  - W.S. Gates journal, circa 1872-1881 (Box 5)
  - Loose material and notes, circa 1907-1947 (Box 5)
  - Journals, 1907-1955; 8 folders (Box 5)
- Academic and research material, 1908-1963; 1 linear foot
  The Academic and research material series (1908-1963, 1 linear foot) documents Gates's efforts and contains information regarding Gates's time in the Philippines in the form of notes, drafts, and completed papers primarily on the topic of vegetation on the islands; writings that describe the many expeditions made by Gates during his tenure in the region; a March, 1910 issue of The Philippine Journal of Science, which includes annotated maps of routes traveled by Gates in the Philippines from 1913 to 1915; a bibliography of Gates's works as well as several works that he authored, such as The Revegetation of Taal Volcano," "Things a Traveler may see in Philippine Forests," and "Philippine Vegetation"; notebooks that document Gates's research interests, particularly birding; and geneaological material.
  - Birding notebooks, 1904; 1906-1912; 1917-1918; 8 folders (Box 7)
  - Botany notebook, circa 1905-1906 (Box 4)
  - Notes, drafts, and completed papers describing the vegetation in the Philippine Islands (Box 1)
  - Descriptions and observations from several expeditions on the Philippine Islands (Box 1)
  - List of publications, 1908-1940; 1949-1954 (Box 4)
  - Journal: The Philippine Journal of Science, Vol. V, March 1910 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous publication, 1917-1918 (Box 4)
  - Geneaology, F.C. Gates, 1919; circa 1942; circa 1946; circa 1948; circa 1951 (Box 4)
  - Papers and other material (includes photograph), circa 1922-1958 (with gaps) (Box 4)
  - Personnel records, correspondence, and other material, circa 1926-1953 (scattered) (Box 4)
  - Articles, birding notes, and other material, circa 1927-1955; 1963 (Box 4)
  - "The Bogs of Northern Lower Michigan" by Frank C. Gates, 1942 (Box 4)
- Visual material, 1907-1927; 1935; 3.4 linear feet
  The Visual material series (1907-1927 and 1935, 3.4 linear feet) consists of photographs, photograph albums (with accompanying photograph logs), negatives, lantern slides, and postcards that document Gates's personal and professional life.
  The albums created by Gates (and his contemporaries at the University of the Philippines) capture the images of his journey throughout the Philippine Islands, primarily local customs, general travel views of people and places, and vegetation; his lengthy journey home through Japan, China, the Hawaiian Islands, and the Western United States; and trips that he and his family took. He has assigned a number to each image. Many of these numbers correspond to the negatives also in this series. The negatives are contained in 105 envelopes and arranged numerically in the box. It is important to note that in this box, there are additional negatives in which the original photograph is not contained in the albums. These negatives cover the years immediately following Gates's return from the Philippines. Also included in this series is a small box of lantern slides produced from select negatives from the Philippines trip, as well as slides used by Gates in academic course instruction (at the University of Michigan Biological Station among other institutions). The final material in this series consists of a box of postcards collected throughout Gates' stay in the Philippines and on his voyage home through Japan and China.
  - Photographs and photograph albums, 1907-1927
    - Chicago, Illinois; Beach; Wisconsin trips, circa 1907-1923 (with gaps) (Box 6)
    - Illinois: Urbana; Hanover; Havana; Carthage., circa 1909-1910; circa 1916-1918 (Box 6)
    - Photos by Frank C. Gates (FCG) from RR in California 1915 to Grand Canyon and Petrified Forest and assorted photos of Colorado by Gleason, circa 1910-1915 (with gaps) (Box 6)
    - Michigan snap shots, August 1911 (Box 5)
    - Michigan: Portage; Ann Arbor; Indiana; Michigan, Detroit mark 4857, circa 1911-1912; circa 1915-1916 (Box 6)
    - Philippine photographs, circa 1912-1915 (Box 5)
    - Philippine photos (loose), circa 1912-1915 (Box 4)
    - Philippine Island photographs (loose), circa 1913-1915 (Box 4)
    - October 1912-July 1913 (Box 1)
      (593-1200)
    - July 1913-November 1913 (Box 1)
      (1201-2200)
    - November 1913-May 1914 (Box 1)
      (2201-2800)
    - May 1914-November 1914 (Box 1)
      (2801-3400)
    - November 1914-March 1915 (Box 2)
      (3401-4038)
    - China, Japan, Hawaii, Ocean (4039-4462), 1913-May 1915 (Box 2)
    - Philippine Islands, 1913-1915 (Box 2)
    - Michigan photograph album, circa 1915-1921 (Box 6)
    - Kansas, 1919-1927 (Box 6)
    - Douglas Lake, 1922-1926 (Box 6)
    - Index to Photograph Albums (Box 2)
    - Photograph album log for negatives (#0001-#4622), circa 1899-1915 (Box 6)
    - Photograph album log for negatives (#4623-#7843) and memo films A-Q, 1915-1954 (Box 6)
  - Lantern slides, circa 1912-1915; circa 1935; 1948
    - Views of the Philippine Islands and Japan, circa 1915 (Box 2)
    - Philippine Islands slides (in box marked "Ecological Slides of F.C. Gates"), circa 1912-1915 (Box 2)
    - Michigan slides, circa 1935; circa 1948 (Box 2)
    - Educational slides (Box 2)
  - Postcards
    - Views of the Philippine Islands, Japan, and China, 500 postcards (approximate) (Box 8)
  - Photographic negatives
    - Nos. 608-5435, 105 envelopes (Box 3)
See also the Bentley Historical Library's David M. Gates papers for additional materials related to Frank Gates as well as for personal and professional records of his son, David M. Gates (former University of Michigan Professor of Botany and Director of the University of Michigan Biological Station).